<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters patents made by the French King, declaring his intent touching those of the reformed religion Published in Roane in the Court of Parliament the seuenth day of Iune, an. 1621. With two letters of the Assembly at Rochell vnto the Duke de Lesdiguieres.</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844486</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844486</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9303</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06370)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9303)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 845:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters patents made by the French King, declaring his intent touching those of the reformed religion Published in Roane in the Court of Parliament the seuenth day of Iune, an. 1621. With two letters of the Assembly at Rochell vnto the Duke de Lesdiguieres.</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
                  <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
                  <author>France. Parlement (Normandy). Proceedings. 1621-06-07.</author>
                  <author>Eglises réformées de France. Assemblée générale (1620-1621 : La Rochelle)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Beale?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXI. [1621]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letters dated at end: Niort the 27 day of May, anno 1621.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>With an extract from the register of the Court of Parliament, dated Roane, 7 June 1621.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eglises réformées de France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9303:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LETTERS PATENTS MADE BY THE FRENCH KING, DECLARING his intent
touching thoſe of the <hi>Reformed Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed in Roane in the Court of Parliament the ſeuenth day
of Iune, An. 1621.</p>
            <p>With two Letters of the Aſſembly at Rochell vnto the Duke de
Leſdiguieres.</p>
            <p>PRINTED MDCXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters_patent">
            <pb facs="tcp:9303:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9303:2"/>
            <head>Letters Pattents made by the French King, declaring his intent
touching thoſe of the reformed Religion. Publiſhed in Roane in the Court of
Parliament the 7 day of Iune, An. 1621.</head>
            <p>THe Kings Letters Patents dated in Niort the 27 day of May laſt
paſt, touching the protection of his ſubiects profeſſing the reformed
Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſhall continue in obedience and ſubiection vnto his Edicts,
and obſeruing thoſe points that are therein contained, againſt the
inhabitants and others, of what ſtate and condition ſoeuer they be,
dwelling, retiring, or withdrawne for refuge in the townes of Rochell and
<hi>S. Iohn d'Angely,</hi> and all others that fauour them, directly or
indirectly, as the ſaid Letters Pattents more at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, bêing
iudicially read, publiſhed and heard, by the Kings Attourney generall in his
concluſions. The ſaid Court hath ordained and ordaineth, that vpon the
backe ſide of the ſaid Letters pattents ſhal be ſet read, publiſhed,
regiſtred and heard, at the requeſt of the Kings Attourney Generall, and
order taken that the copies of the ſame in print ſhall be ſent not onely
to the generall Courts, but alſo to euery particular Bailiwicks and
Vice-counties of reſort, there alſo to be read, publiſhed and regiſtred
in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place of iuriſdiction, and kept and obſerued according to the
forme and tenour thereof, enioyning all Iudges and ſubſtitutes of the
ſaid Attourney Generall, euery one in particular to put their helping hands
for and vnto the obſeruation, and puniſhment of the contradictors thereof,
vpon paine to anſwer the ſame perſonally; and to aduertiſe the ſaid
Court what diligence they haue vſed therein, as well touching the
publication, as the execution of the ſaid Letters pattents within the ſpace
of a moneth next enſuing, according to the order therein taken by this Court
this preſent day. The contents of the ſaid Letters pattents being as
followeth. <pb facs="tcp:9303:3"/> 
               <q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="letters_patent">
                           <p>
                              <hi>LOVIS</hi> by the grace of God King of France and
Nauarre, To all men whom theſe preſents ſhall come to be ſeene or read,
greeting. The deſire that we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies had to preſerue publicke peace
and tranquillitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſubiects, and to impeach thoſe euils and
deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations which leuying of armes ordinarily bringeth with it, as alſo
thoſe oppreſſions and calamities that our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereby receiue, hath
moued vs diuers moneths toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther patiently to tollerate and ſuffer the
exceſſes, diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and rebellions that haue bin committed in diuers
Townes of our Realme by ſome of our ſubiects making profeſſion of the
reformed Religion, ſpecially in Rochell, Montaban and others, wherein there
hath bin, and as yet are holden vnlawfull aſſemblies, which are rather
employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to forme and erect popular eſtates &amp; commonwealths, then to
containe themſelues within the limits of that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto vs whereunto
they are naturally bound: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing cauſed a Seale to be grauen, and vnder the
ſame, and the hands of the principall perſons of the ſaid aſſemblies,
they haue made diuers ordinances, decrees, meſſages, and commiſſions,
containing power vnto particular aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, to command in prouinces and
townes, to leuie the moneys of our farmes and receits, to leuie men, armes and
mony, to melt and caſt cannons, to ſend meſſages to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine realmes
and prouinces, and other ſuch like actions, which ſufficiently make an
apparence of a greater rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and open riſing againſt our authoritie;
whereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed and truly certified in the moneth of April laſt; and
knowing that they embolden themſelues to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into theſe diſorders
becauſe of the little ſuretie that they ſay they haue of their perſons
and libertie of their conſciences, by our declaration made and bearing date
the 24. of the ſaid moneth of April, deſiring to giue them all
aſſurances of our good inclinations towards thoſe that ſhall continue
in their duties, and receiuing them into our particular protection and
ſauegard: we declared and made knowne, that the voyage which we pretended to
make<pb facs="tcp:9303:3"/>into thoſe quarters, was (by our approching to thoſe
pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where the ſaid inſolencies are committed) there to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh
and make our authoritie to appeare; to the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe that ſhall
be found culpable, rather then to vſe any other greater rigour; nor yet to
ſhew that power which God hath giuen vnto vs for the puniſhment of ſuch
inſolencies: but they are ſo farre from looking into their owne
imperfections, and reducing themſelues vnto that whereunto they are obliged,
that the greateſt part of them continuing in their bad pretences, openly run
into rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and commit all ſorts of hoſtilitie againſt thoſe that
will not ioyne with them: openly publiſhing that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no other
head then the aſſembly that is in Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell, which hath cauſed diuers
ſouldiers leuied by the ſaid commiſſions to gather together in Saint
Iohn de Angely, that make ſhew to withſtand our entrance therein by force
of arms, which enforceth vs (perceiuing alſo that the ſame diſorder hath
followed in diuers other Townes of our Realme) to make preparation to puniſh
the offenders according to their merits and deſerts, and to that effect
together with the ordinarie courſe of iuſtice, to vſe the meanes that God
hath giuen vs for the maintenance of our authoritie: And to the end that all
our ſubiects, and ſpecially thoſe that make profeſſion of the
reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion may not be abuſed by falſe pretences, wherewith the
ſaid aſſembly ſerue themſelues, to diuert and turne them from their
duties, and that both the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be informed of our intents and
wils touching the ſame. We by the aduice of the Princes, Dukes, Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>res, Officers of our Crowne, and the
principall perſons of our Councell, haue made knowne and declared, make known
and declare by theſe preſents, that concerning our ſaid Letters pattents
bearing date the 24 of April laſt, we haue taken and receiued, and take and
receiue into our prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſpeciall ſauegard all our ſubiects of
the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, of what qualitie or condition ſoeuer they be,
that ſhall continue and remaine in our obedience<pb facs="tcp:9303:4"/>and vnder the
obſeruation of our Edicts, which we will alſo cauſe to be diligently and
carefully obſerued in fauor of them: but perceiuing the manifeſt rebellions
that are committed in our Towne of Rochell, not onely by the aſſembly which
is alwayes continued contrary to our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe prohibitions, but alſo by
the whole body of the ſaid Towne, Burgeſſes and inhabitants thereof, as
alſo that which is done in our Towne of Saint Iohn d'Angely, and the acts of
hoſtillitie which they dayly commit againſt our perſon. Wee haue
declared, and by theſe preſents de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, all the inhabitants and other
perſons, of what eſtate and qualities ſoeuer they be, which at this
preſent dwell, are retired and refuged within the townes of Rochell and Saint
Iohn d'Angely, and all others that fauour them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly, or that
ſhall haue acceſſe vnto, intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, aſſociation and
correſpondence with them, or that ſhall allow in any ſort whatſoeuer of
the ſaid aſſembly in Rochell, or the other aſſemblies, circuites,
counſels of prouinces, or other congregations that haue correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
with that of Rochell, and that are holden without our expreſſe
permiſſion; relapſed and fallen into diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and guiltie of high
treaſon, and as ſuch their lands and goods to be forfet and confiſcated
vnto vs: willing that proceſſe ſhould be made againſt them, according
to the rigour of our lawes and ordinances, by the ſeiſures of their
perſons, inuentories of their goods, and other wayes ordinary and
accuſtomed, vſed in ſuch caſes. Declaring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo our ſaid Townes of
Saint Iohn d'Angely and Rochell, and all others their adherents, and which with
them ſhall take part in the ſaid crimes and diſobediences, to be
depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of, and to haue forfeited all their rights, priuiledges,
franchiſes, and other benefits that haue bin giuen and granted vnto them by
the Kings our predeceſſors, and by vs. And to the end that wee may
diſcerne and know the good from the bad, we will that all our ſubiects
making profeſſion of the ſaid reformed Religion, as well Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and
officers, as others of what qualitie or condition<pb facs="tcp:9303:4"/>ſoeuer they be,
and alſo the townes and commonalties of the ſaid qualitie, ſhall make
declaration, in the Preſidents Courts, Bailiwicks, and ſtuardſhips of
their reſorts, of their good intents touching our ſeruice; and that in the
ſame they ſhall renounce and diſauow, as alſo proteſt, not to adhere
in any maner to the ſaid aſſembly of Rochell, nor to any other
aſſemblies, counſels, of prouinces, circuites, reſorts, and others,
which (as it is ſaid) haue bin and are holden without our expreſſe
permiſſion; and that with vs they will oppoſe themſelues againſt all
the reſolutions that therein may haue bin taken, whereof they ſhall haue
teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies from the ſaid Courts, &amp;c. neceſſary and fit for their
diſcharges. As alſo we expreſly prohibite all Gentlemen and others, not
to permit their children, ſeruants, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers depending on them, to go into
the ſaid townes, nor to lend them any comfort or aſſiſtance
whatſoeuer, nor yet to lodge or receine into their houſes thoſe that
ſhall go thither or conuerſe with them in any manner whatſoeuer, vpon
paine to be holden culpable of the ſame crime. Moſt expreſly willing and
charging all Bailies, Stuards, Prouoſt Marſhals, Iudges, and their
Lieutenants, Deputie Stuards, Prouoſt Marſhals of our couſins the
Conſtable, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals of France, and all other our Officers to whom it
may appertaine, exactly and carefully to proceed againſt the perſons and
goods of thoſe that ſhall haue incurred the ſaid crime; and to our
Attourneys Generall and their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes, vpon the ſaid
proceſſeſſes to make diligent and requiſite enquiries, ſuch as are
to be done by them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of any ſafegard or other
aſſurances, that they may obtaine from vs, by falſe ſuggeſtions or
otherwiſe, if the ſaid ſauegards be not made by Letters Patents ſealed
with our great Seale; and that in the ſame it be expreſly ſet downe that
we haue giuen them licence to go into, or frequent the ſaid rebellious
townes. We alſo will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire our louing and faithfull Counſellours
that ſit in our Courts of Parliament, and chambers of Edicts, to cauſe
theſe our preſent Letters pattents to be read, publiſhed,<pb facs="tcp:9303:5"/>and
regiſtred in euery place, and the contents thereof to be exactly kept and
obſerued according to the forme and tenour thereof: enioyning our Attourneys
Generall and their ſubſtitutes to be carefull thereof, and to make all
proceſſes and purſuites neceſſary and requiſite touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the
ſame, for ſuch is our will and pleaſure. In witneſſe whereof, we haue
cauſed our Seale to be ſet hereunto.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at Niort 
<date>the 27 day of May, Anno 1621. and of our raigne the
twelfth.</date>
                              </dateline> 
                              <signed>Signed, <hi>LOVIS.</hi>
                              </signed> And on the backe
ſide, 
<signed> 
                                 <hi>Par le Roy. Potier.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>And ſealed with the great Seale in yellow waxe. And
further, on the back ſide is written, 
<q> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="postscript">
                           <p>Read, publiſhed, regiſtred, and heard at the
inſtance and requeſt of the Kings Attourney Generall, to be executed, kept
and obſerued according to the forme and tenour. By force of the decree
contained in the regiſter of this day.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>At Roane in the Court of Parliament 
<date>the 7. day of Iune, 1621.</date>
                              </dateline> 
                              <signed>Signed, <hi>De Bois
leveſque.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="extracts_from_register">
            <head>EXTRACTED OVT OF THE REGISTER of the Court of
Parliament.</head>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="extract">
                        <p>THe Court of the Chambers being aſſembled, hauing
ſeene the Kings Letters patents dated in Niort the 27 of May laſt, as well
for the protection and ſafegard of all his ſubiects of the reformed
Religion, that ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in, and containe themſelues vnder his
obedience, and the obſeruation of his Edicts, making profeſſion thereof
as his ſaid Letters patents ſpecifie and declare, againſt the inhabitants
and other perſons of what eſtate and qualitie ſoeuer they be, that dwell,
continue, retire, and are reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Townes of Rochell and Saint Iohn
d'Angely, and all others that fauour them directly or indirectly, and the
concluſions of the Kings Attourney Generall being<pb facs="tcp:9303:5"/>conſidered.
The ſaid Court, the Chambers being aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, hath and doth ordaine that
the ſaid Letters patents ſhall be read, publiſhed and regiſtred, that
the contents thereof may be executed, kept and obſerued according to their
forme and tenour, without any attribution neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe of any
iuriſdiction and knowledge in that reſpect to the Prouoſts Generall,
their Lieutenants or Vicebailies; vnleſſe it be onely for the execution of
the ſaid decrees &amp; reaſons, the priſoners being caried and committed
to the ordinary priſons of the ſaid places, and their proceſſe made,
and iudged by the ſaid ordinary Regall Iudges, and by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale in the ſaid
Court, and vpon expreſſe charge, that the declarations mentioned by the
ſaid Letters patents ſhall by them of the ſaid reformed Religion be made,
as well by the maiſters of houſholds, their children, retinue and
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, aboue 16. yeares of age, as alſo by widowes and women, that is
ſuch as reſide and dwell in the townes and ſuburbes of the ſame within
eight dayes after the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid Letters patents; and thoſe
that dwell in the countrey, or are abſent from the ſaid townes, within
fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene dayes after the ſaid publication, vpon the paines and penalties
containedin the ſaid Letters patents; which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations ſhall be made
before the Bailies or their Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the open Court, according to the forme
thereof printed, and which ſhall be ſent by the ſaid Court, to be
deliuered freely without any fees paying to thoſe that ſhall make the
ſame declaration, as well by the Indges and Clarkes vpon paine of
puniſhment.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Dated in Roane in the ſaid Court of
Parliament, the Chambers being aſſembled, 
<date>the ſeuenth of Iune, 1621.</date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>Signed, <hi>De Bois
leveſque.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="extract">
                        <p>THis day <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> the
<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>_…</desc>
                           </gap> day of
<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 1621. hath appeared before vs,
<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                           </gap> appearing,
<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                           </gap> dwelling in the Pariſh of
<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                           </gap> aged
<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>_…</desc>
                           </gap> yeares, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, making
profeſſion of the reformed Religion, who<pb facs="tcp:9303:6"/>to fulfill the Kings
Letters patents made at Niort the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and twentieth day of May laſt
paſt, hath declared, ſworne and promiſed to continue, liue and die in the
fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie and obedience which hee oweth vnto the King; To renounce,
diſauouch and proteſt, not to adhere in any manner vnto the aſſembly of
Rochell, neither vnto any other aſſemblies, counſels of Prouinces,
reſorts, circuites and others, that are holden, hold, and ſhall be holden
without the expreſſe commiſſion of the King, but rather with his
Maieſtie to oppoſe himſelfe againſt all the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions that therein
may, haue bin, and are taken. In wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whereof, the ſaid
<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                           </gap> hath ſigned vnto the Clerkes
Regiſter; and whereupon we haue deliuered vnto him this preſent writing
ſigned by vs and one of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Clerkes of this Bailiwicke,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>The day and yeare
aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:9303:6"/>
            <head>Letters ſent by thoſe of the reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
aſſembled together in Rochell.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Duke de Leſdiguieres.</head>
                  <p>MAy it pleaſe your Honour, wee haue refrained from anſwering
vnto the two firſt letters, which it pleaſed you to write vnto vs, for an
anſwer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our former, ſtaying till the Gentleman that wee ſent vnto
you, had more particularly reported vnto vs your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion touching the ſtate
of our preſent affaires, as he hath done, hauing at large declared vnto vs
your aduice and good intent to aide our Churches, to recouer that peace,
ſuretie and contentment which wee ſeeke for, from the bountie of our King,
when you ſhall haue meanes to ſpeak vnto his Maieſtie, to whom (as you
haue certified vnto vs) you intend to ride. This your Honours good affection,
whereof without doubt we aſſure our ſelues, moueth vs vnto thoſe moſt
humble thankes which we are bound to yeeld vnto you, and augmenteth our
deſire (together with theſe preſents) to ſatisfie your two firſt
letters, as the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of our entire iuſtification, which your
deſire to know, requireth at our hands, hoping that your Honour hauing
reiected all doubts and ſcruples which ſeeme to hold you at a ſtay
touching the purſuite of our conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſtaying in this place, as we
may eaſily do it, you will eaſily thinke it fit to ioyne your good will
with our ſubmiſſions, for obtaining the fruites and effects of our moſt
humble requeſts and ſupplications to his Maieſtie; and by that meanes
bereaue our enemies of their triumphs which they make againſt vs, vpon the
doubt which you ſeeme to make of the euidence of our good meanings by your
firſt letter, which to that effect they haue publiſhed. Whereupon we
beſeech your Honour to be pleaſed, for the reſoluing of all theſe
difficulties, that we may put you in mind, that the reſolution that we then
made of our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration at London, to reaſſemble againe vpon default of 
<pb facs="tcp:9303:7"/>performance of ſuch things as were promiſed vnto vs, was
grounded vpon the promiſe which was giuen to you and to <hi>Monſieur de
Chaſtillon,</hi> by my Lord the Prince, and the Duke <hi>de Luynes,</hi> in
the Kings name, and by you vnto vs; which our Churches hauing faithfully
obſerued, vpon that condition confirmed their Deputies in all Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or
ſubſtituted others to meete here if occaſion fell out. It is
needleſſe to produce other proofes, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe our regiſters to
put you in minde, that as then thoſe promiſes were made vnto vs, vpon
condition to reaſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble together if they were not performed within the
time prefixed: ſeeing that your Honour is the moſt ſufficient wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neſſe that wee may or can produce, which acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
and once againe confirme the truth thereof by your ſecond letter dated the 22
of February laſt, where you writ vnto vs in proper termes, that the ſame
that was granted vnto vs then vpon the ſeperation at Loudun (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on promiſe
to reaſſemble) hath bin entirely executed, whereof we will hereafter
ſpeake, hauing firſt manifeſted this permiſſion which you deferre to
be made euident, and which we eſteeme ought to be thought and iudged
auail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and ſufficient without contradiction, and to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of
thoſe that are moſt ſcrupulous; if we adde thereunto, that beſides the
interuention of my ſaid Lord the Prince, and of my Lord the Duke <hi>de
Luynes,</hi> of whom the eminent qualitie in the one, and the great fauour of
the other, can permit no ſhadow of diſauouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, our good intents haue bin
much more ſetled vpon the expreſſe word ſpoken from the mouth of his
ſacred Maieſtie, whereof you are an vnreproueable witnes, when you told vs
by your firſt letter bearing date the firſt of the ſaid Moneth, in
theſe words, ſaying that the ſame which your Honour had promiſed vnto
vs in his Maieſties name, was confirmed at Fontainebleau by his Royall mouth
to the Deputies of the aſſembly at Loudun, at ſuch time as they certified
him of the ſeparation. We thinke it had not bin lawfull for vs to deſire or
to imagine any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion<pb facs="tcp:9303:7"/>more auailable or firmer
aſſurance, then the ſacred word of the King. Inke and paper cannot
conferre any weight nor authoritie to the Kings words. And certainly we would
haue iudged our ſelues to be vnworthy of the fauour of our King, and
iniurious to his authoritie, if we had required that permiſſion vnder a
greater ſecuritie then his Maieſties word. VVhereupon we beſeech your
Honor to pardon vs, if we tell you, that then we asked no note in writing, and
that it was not denied vnto vs. To the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary it is true, that when we were
preſſed to ſeparate our ſelues, we were offered a note in writing to
reaſſemble if iuſtice were not done vnto vs. And many times by diuers of
the principal, this ſpeech was confirmed in open Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to our Deputies,
that they did not doubt but that we would reaſſemble together. But we that
feare nothing more then thoſe paines, and ſuch encounters which our
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies alwayes imagine and deuiſe to do miſchiefe vnto vs, at that time
deſired and inſiſted to receiue ſome reall contentment vpon our
complaints, thereby to aſſure the aſtoniſhment and the perplexities of
our brethren, and to reſtraine the inſolencie of our enemies, by ſuch
teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of our protection and of the Kings good will towards vs, that we
might come thither no more, nor fall againe into ſuch labyrinths. But all our
inſtances could preuaile nothing, and we were conſtrained to content our
ſelues with thoſe promiſes; from whence our enemies by their ſecret
reaches knew well how to draw thoſe inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and miſchiefes which we
foreſee and too well appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. Seeing then that the aſſurance and
permiſſion of our reaſſembling was ſuch, what need was there (as your
Honour ſaith) that our generall Deputies ſhould renew their inſtance to
the King, to permit vs to do it? It had bin a meanes to call in queſtion an
aſſured promiſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to preiudice our ſelues. For we feare not
to tell you that which cannot be concealed from you, that our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies haue by
many experiences made vs feele, that as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and whenſoeuer thoſe things
that are moſt aſſured<pb facs="tcp:9303:8"/>vnto vs either by Edicts or by other
grants from the King, fall in queſtion, they haue that power to cauſe that
to be withdrawne that was granted vnto vs, and to cauſe vs to loſe that
right which we had obtained. VVe could ſhew an infinite number of complaints
vpon this ſubiect, and how that diuers articles concerning the
ſtrengthening of things to vs formerly granted, and afterward infringed, we
haue receiued anſwers directly contrary vnto the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent grants, and
ſuch as wholy annihilated them. Then who doubts not, but that the ſame
power of our enemies, which at this day worketh the deniall of thoſe things
that were promiſed vnto vs, would not alſo haue cauſed all the requeſts
of our Deputies to be reiected. Hauing thus iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vnto your Honour our
ſaid permiſſion, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the equitie of our proceeding
authorized by the ſame; it reſteth onely plainly to ſhew you the
occaſions, condition and neceſſitie of our reaſſembling, and to haue
recourſe vnto our complaints. The circumſtances of the time, and of that
which hath bin omitted or committed contrary to the promiſes, ſhall
ſuffice therein. Your Honor remembreth, and your letter mentioneth the
ſame, that the King promiſed vs that within ſixe moneths from the day of
our ſeparation, he would cauſe Leytoure to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, admit the
Counſellours of the Religion into the Parliament of Paris, giue a writing
touching the guarding of the places of ſecuritie; that the ſtates thereof
ſhould be deliuered vnto vs; that our requeſts ſhould be fauourably
anſwered, and the anſwers thereunto duly and truly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted. And touching
the affaires of Bearn, that within ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen moneths the Deputies of the country
ſhould be heard touching that which they would ſhew vnto his Maieſtie.
Our ſeparation was made vpon the 13 of April the laſt yeare, the ſix
moneths from the ſame day fell vpon the 13 of October following: and in all
that time nothing of thoſe things that were promiſed was executed, but
onely the deliuery of the writing touching the guard of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, what
inſtance and purſuite ſoeuer our Deputies gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall<pb facs="tcp:9303:8"/>could
make. In the ſame time the King went to Bearn, during the delay obtained for
our remonſtrances, and they being not vnderſtood, nor once hearkned vnto;
not onely the commiſſion to the contrary hath bin executed, but which is
more, our Churches haue loſt all the ſecuritie and libertie which they had
enioyed in that country <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> many
yeares together, and in an inſtant followed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all thoſe
dangerous conſequences which we doubted from the beginning of the decree of
the contrary commiſſion. Vpon that time the ſixe moneths being paſt,
this griefe hapned, and none of the reſt redreſſed; our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly
vpon the 25 of Nouember. And if ſince that the towne of Leytoure hath bin
remitted into the hands of a Gentleman of the Religion, could the healing of
that old ſore ſo long time ſuffered, after the feeling of a much greater
griefe, be a ſufficient meanes to ſtay our humble complaints, touching the
ſame and all the reſt. We were already aſſembled, and our moſt humble
complaints pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto his Maieſtie, when the two Counſellors were
admitted, but vpon a worſe condition then all the former refuſals, which
bereaue vs of the libertie which the King granteth vnto vs by his Edicts, to
enter indifferently in the office, in ſuch manner, that the ſame griefe is
ſo far from being redreſſed, that it is rather increaſed by that
meanes. Theſe therefore, and it pleaſe your Honor, were the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of
our reaſſembling, which yet continueth. The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate of Bearn,
the deniall of the ſtate of the places of ſecuritie in Dauphinois, which is
openly maintained, (contrary to the promiſe made vnto you, and which you here
confirmed vnto vs by your letters) was neuer gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs. To the contrary
whereof, your Honor knows, that particularly from <hi>anno</hi> 1616. at the
conference of Loudun, it was particularly vnto vs, and ſince that by the
laſt promiſes confirmed vnto your ſelf. As alſo, beſides the publike
teſtimonies which you giue vs here, you may call to minde, that you haue
confirmed the ſame to diuers men in particular, telling them of the
abſolute neceſſitie that<pb facs="tcp:9303:9"/>we haue to purſue the ſame. Then
followeth the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction made againſt the 27. article of the Edict,
touching our admiſſion into offices. The fauourable anſwers denied to our
propoſitions; and the ſending of Committees into the Prouinces neglected.
And laſtly the troupes and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons left in the country of Bearn, Guyenne
and Poictou, which giue an alarme and a iuſt diſtruſt vnto our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.
Theſe are the principall heads of our complaints; it is not the number, but
the weightineſſe of them which maketh them important. As alſo, that
thoſe few articles, for the reparation whereof we haue hoped to receiue
ſome aſſurance of the Kings good will, from the which our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies by all
meanes ſeeke to eſtrange vs, ought not to be made a conſequence againſt
vs; but on the contrary, our obedience ought thereby to be more manifeſt,
that wee contented our ſelues with that remedie, to ſtrengthen our
patience, beſides all ſo many other infractions that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually hurt our
libertie, which the King hath granted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. And by the ſame reaſon, our
cauſe ought at this day to be more fauoured, and our equitie more
manifeſted, if vpon the not executing of ſo few articles, contrary to the
faithfull promiſes made vnto vs, (whereby our condition being alſo much
impeached) we haue had our recourſe to the fauour of our King, by our moſt
humble declarations, in that ſtate wherein he hath permitted vs to
reaſſemble, to preſent the ſame xnto him. Whereupon we are not able to
expreſſe the intollerable griefe that we feele, when in regard of theſe
proceedings which we haue followed by lawfull meanes of the reſpect and
reuerence that is due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Maieſtie, we perceiue our ſelues to be
condemned by the ſubtill practiſes of our enemies, which ſlander vs to
wrong the Kings authoritie; thereby to kindle his wrath and indignation
againſt vs, ſeeking to reduce vs to that point, either to incurre the
effect of his diſpleaſure by open warre, wherewith we are threatned; or for
to ſhun the ſame we ſhould keepe ſilence in our iuſt complaints and
endure all the wrongs and miſchiefes which daily are throwne<pb facs="tcp:9303:9"/>vpon
vs. So that from henceforth, men will acknowledge no other obedience in vs, but
that we ſhould with patience ſuffer all the miſchiefes that they would do
vnto vs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out permiſſion to complaine thereof: and our griefes and
preuentions made againſt the falſities and threatnings of our enemies,
ſhall be imputed to diſobedience, and a capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall crime. VVill not your
Honour iudge, that there is a meane to be vſed in theſe things? but rather
acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it ſeemes vnto you, that the permiſſion which hath bin
giuen vnto vs by his Maieſtie to reaſſemble, and the importance of the
wrongs, either not redreſſed, but rather increaſed, purge our
aſſembly of the blame to be vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or done without authoritie; we hope
that you will thinke it more reaſonable to employ that good affection which
it pleaſeth you to promiſe vs, and that authoritie and credit which the
greatneſſe and innumerable number of ſo commendable ſeruices haue
gotten you with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, to make him to vnderſtand the ſinceritie
of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and the neceſſitie of our iuſt complaints rather then to
ſeeke our ſeparation before ſome contentment be giuen vnto our Churches;
whoſe diſquietneſſe makes vs the more carefull to perſiſt in
procuring their conſolation. VVhich to attaine, we haue ſought to enter
into thoſe wayes of reſpect which we beare vnto our King, that might cleare
vs of that imputation which our enemies ſeeke to imprint in him towards vs.
To that end hauing deſired our generall Deputies, being by them certified of
the continuall refuſall which is made to heare them in our names, to
repreſent our iuſt demands in their owne, and the names of all our
Churches. VVherein we perſwade our ſelues that your Honour approuing our
proceeding, and therein fauouring our ſaid generall Deputies, you wil alſo
iudge that with moſt iuſt reaſon we haue giuen them to vnderſtand vpon
the propoſition, where by their laſt diſpatch, we haue bin certified what
is done at the Court, that is, (not to giue vs any contentment, and to binde vs
to a ſeparation, vpon a pardon to be giuen vs) that our<pb facs="tcp:9303:10"/>conſciences and the care of the honour and good of our Churches,
will neuer permit vs to conſent vnto ſuch a thing, that with it would draw
not onely a great opproby vpon our Religion, but alſo procure the totall
ruine of our affaires. VVhereupon we haue bin deſirous to informe your Honour
of our opinions and reſolutions, to the end that it might pleaſe you,
according to the fauour which you promiſe vnto vs, rather to ſignifie vnto
his Maieſtie, that when his Royall bountie ſhall think it good to grant
thoſe fauours which our Churches require of him in all humilitie, (thereby to
quench in ſo many peoples mindes the diſtruſts which the miſchiefes
that we endure, and the continuall threatnings of our enemies haue imprinted
therein) it will be a meanes more and more to confirme his authoritie, and make
it the ſame which the incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wiſedome of his father the late King
deceaſed, alwayes maintained, grounding the peace and tranquillitie of his
eſtate vpon the maintenance of his Edicts. Vnder the force whereof, we
deſire not any further libertie then onely to continue the obedience that wee
haue alwayes yeelded without reproch vnto our Kings That (and it pleaſe your
Honour) is the good which we beſeech you to contribute vnto the preſent
eſtate of our affaires, as we haue diuers times humbly required the reſt of
the great perſonages to do the like, and then ſpecially when for the
preuention of the ruine of all our affaires by the diuiſion which we
perceiued men went about to ſow betweene them and vs, we beſought them not
to hearken vnto a conference pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto them, tending from henceforth to
annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and make fruitleſſe all the purſuites that wee take in hand,
by the order eſtabliſhed betweene vs by the Kings permiſſion; and which
is more, to lay on them and all of vs the burthen of refuſals or of deceits,
ſuch as wherewith our euill willers delude the promiſes which the King hath
made vnto vs. Which we eſteeming it to be no leſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to
themſelues then to the generalitie of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, we are perſwaded that
we are bound in conſcience<pb facs="tcp:9303:10"/>to beſeech you ill, not to giue way
thereunto. Which we deſire your Honour alſo to accept of, and not to be a
meanes of excluding that good and aduantage which your authoritie and fauour,
ioyning with our iuſt requeſts, may procure vnto vs. For we do not
deſire, neither haue we any other intent in the diſcharging of the offices
giuen vnto vs, but as much as poſſible we may, to ſtrengthen the band of
our vnion between all the members of our body, and ſpecially thoſe of your
rank and qualitie, and which is more conſiderable. So farre off are we from
ſeeking any wayes or meanes to ouerthrow our ſelues, by making a
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration betweene you and vs, that to the contrary, ſince we haue bin
here, we haue had nothing in more nor grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter recommendation then to re-vnite
the particulars and the generall, by a coniunction of intereſt, and one
ſelf ſame affection towards the aduancement of the glory of God and the
good of our Churches, vnder the obedience of his Maieſtie. VVherein we are
bound to render thankes vnto God, that not onely the townes' and commonalties
of our Religion, but alſo all thoſe that hold a greater ranke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs,
haue made knowne the moſt particular aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their conſtancie in
our vnion: as your Honour alſo, by the proteſtation which you haue made
vnto vs of the ſame, and of the continuance of your ſeruices towards the
Church of God, in the profeſſion of our Religion, hath done. VVhereupon we
muſt tell you, that the ſlanders im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently publiſhed by thoſe that
hate your vertue, becauſe of your profeſſion, could neuer ſhake nor
diminiſh our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions therein. And in that confidence, and vpon the
ſingular aſſurances that <hi>Monſieur de Bonnet</hi> hath giuen vs of
your good affection to procure (by the Kings fauour) ſome contentment to our
Churches in theſe occurrents. We beſeech your Honour once againe to
contribute your good will therein, in ſuch manner, that diſperſing that
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation which our enemies maliciouſly lay on vs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the Kings
authoritie, our ſincere intents being knowne, our Churches by our ſure and
honorable returne<pb facs="tcp:9303:11"/>vnto them, may vpon their moſt important
complaints receiue that good which they ſo long time haue hoped, and
promiſed vnto them, being ſo neceſſarie for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation and
tranquillitie. And that ſo the peace of the State being fully confirmed,
according to our deſires, and that of all good French men, we may ſee the
arbiterment of Chriſtendome in the hands of our King. And your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by
his commandement, in many of his beſt ſubiects by your victorious hands,
make the terror of his name and of his forces, ſtrike into his enemies
hearts, who with great deſire now more then euer they did, ſeeke to
imbaſe the authoritie and the dignitie of this monarchie, which for the good
thereof and of the Church is therein reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. God increaſe your yeares,
and his graces in you, to whom we alwayes remaine your Honours moſt humble
and moſt affectionate ſeruants. The Deputies of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches in
France, and the ſoueraigntie of Bearn aſſembled in Rochell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed, 
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De la Creſſonniere,</hi> Preſident.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Roſell,</hi> Lieutenant.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De la Piterne,</hi> Secretarie.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De la Tour,</hi> Secretarie.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed> 
                     <dateline>Rochell 
<date>the 18 of March, 1621.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9303:11"/>
                  <head>The ſecond Letter written by the Aſſembly in Rochell,
to the Duke de Deſdiguieres, dated the ſecond of April, 1621.</head>
                  <p>THe Letter which it pleaſed your Honour to write vnto vs, we
haue receiued by <hi>Monſieur de la Roche,</hi> who withall hath particularly
aduertiſed vs of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. We perſwade our ſelues that you would not
haue ſent this meſſage, nor giuen vs that advice, if you had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
our laſt Letter, which contained the reaſonable grounds of our
aſſembling, together with the iuſtneſſe and neceſſitie of our
ſubſiſtance, and thereby you would haue perceiued that we reiect
formalities, and by onely cleauing vnto the ſpeciall end of our vocation,
which is to redreſſe the euils that our Churches endure, haue giuen
commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our generall Deputies in their owne name, and thoſe of our
ſaid Churches to purſue the iuſtneſſe of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, as you may
more at large vnderſtand the ſame from them by word of mouth. As by all
theſe proceedings we iuſtifie our neceſſary reſolutions vnto your
Honour; ſo it hath bin a moſt great diſpleaſure vnto vs to
vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand your contrary feelings thereof, which ſerue to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end
but to increaſe our iuſt diſtruſts, and to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the euill will
of thoſe that are the hinderances of the effects of our lawfull proceedings.
For to this ſeparation of our aſſemblies, of late time, all the
practiſes of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſpecially tend; which ought ſo much the
more to be ſuſpitious to all the members of our Churches, that they would
bring vs thereunto by ſuch wayes as reduce our affaires into deſolation,
and our bodies into opprobrie. For that by abandoning the meanes of our
ſecuritie, which<pb facs="tcp:9303:12"/>ſo many yeares wee haue ſought with ſo
great care and paines, we ſhall caſt our Churches into new labyrinths,
whereby they ſhould be reduced into deſpaire, and would not omit any manner
of remedy to withdraw themſelues from an vniuſt perſecution. We know how
much we are to attribute vnto the advice which commeth from your Honors great
experience; but may it pleaſe you to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that which hath enſued
contrary to your and our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, of your entermiſe of Loudun, and into how
many bad termes our light credit hath reduced vs, with ſo great apparence to
meete with no better in time to come, if we ſhould commit the like errors. To
the end that you may beare with vs, if the great hurt which that blow gaue vnto
our conſervation, maketh vs incapable of the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which you require
of vs, ſo inſtantly, with your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ioyning the reproches of
diſobedience, and the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of hard vſage; which things we eſteeme
not ſtrange in the enemies of our profeſſion, who with drawing from vs
his Maieſties good inclinations, take pleaſure in ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and
violences, and whom we know are ſufficiently animated not to deſiſt from
the deſolation of the Churches in Bearn. But when thoſe that are ſo much
bound to the tranquillitie of the houſe of God, wherein they had their being,
&amp; ought to leaue an honorable and profitable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of them to their
poſteritie, lift vp their armes againſt our innocencie. It is an affliction
much greater vnto vs then we ſpeake of. For touching the accuſations
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are charged, we expect no greater teſtimonie of the perpetuall
obedience of vs and our fathers, their that of your Honors owne knowledge, who
haue ſo often found, that we were never ſo inſtantly accuſed of
diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, but onely with an intent to withdraw thoſe advantages from
vs, which reaſon, equitie, and the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of our Kings made indubitable.
Theſe devices being not vnknowne vnto you, we expect better things from your
Honour, conformable to the common profeſſion<pb facs="tcp:9303:12"/>which you haue of
vs; being on your part, not onely bound thereunto by expreſſe words, which
to vs ought to be a publicke faith, and conſequently inviolable, but by the
ſerious remembrance of the ranke and authoritie whereunto God hath raiſed
you, by the ſingular bleſſing which he hath beſtowed vpon you,
cauſing it to increaſe together with your yeares, in diuers manner, by the
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his truth, which is none of the leaſt honours you ſhall
carrie with you from hence, by the holy communion that you haue ſo long time
had with the Church of God: by this meanes you ſhall haue this teſtimonie
in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to haue employed Gods talents to the profit of his
Church: whereupon we tell your Honor, that it much importeth the honour of your
profeſſion, to conſider how you put your hand to theſe affaires, which
as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>is pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> are expoſed to the open view of all Chriſtendome,
as a fit meanes which God putteth into your hands to a duance his glorie, and
in good time to bring our Churches into an aſſured eſtate. If it will
pleaſe you to ioyne your cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and fauour to the iuſt proceedings of our
general De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, which will leaue you an honorable mark, and make you liue
alwayes in the memorie of men. And although ſome conſiderations of the
world may moue you to be indifferent touching our ruine, (which we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not
from you) neuertheleſſe we will not diſtruſt in Gods protection, hoping
that he will touch the heart of our King, by the admirable meanes of his
prouidence, in his time to effect a full contentment to his people; whom we
beſeech to make you fully to vnderſtand the malice of our enemies, the
importance of our miſchiefes, the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of our proceedings, and the
equitie of our demands touching the oppreſſion of the afflicted; that being
moved with Chriſtian compaſſion, you may make that power and credit which
he hath given you available, in your days to ſee the proſperitie of the
Church and the ſtate. Theſe are the humble requeſts which we have
alreadie made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<pb facs="tcp:9303:13"/>you by our laſt letters, and which now wee
re-iterate, moſt carneſtly beſeeching you to be aſſured, that both
ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>cularly we are
your Honors</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Moſt humble and moſt affectioned ſeruants,
the Deputies of the reformed Churches of France, and the ſoueraigntie of
Bearn, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Rochell. 
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De la Creſſonniere,</hi> Preſident,</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Roſſell,</hi> Lieutenant.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De la Piterne,</hi> Secretarie.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De la Tour.</hi> Secretarie.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <date>the ſecond of April, 1621.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9303:13"/>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
